Alexander Giovannelli

Phone: +1-740-258-9709Email: agiovannelli@vt.edu Website: agiovannelli.github.io

Summary

My research focuses on the intersection of human-computer interaction (HCI), extended reality (XR), and 3D interaction. I am currently developing and evaluating systems that facilitate both real-time, synchronous collaboration for simultaneous user cooperation, as well as recording and playback functionalities to support asynchronous collaboration over different time periods.

EDUCATION

Virginia Tech Blacksburg, VA, USA

Ph.D. in Computer Science advised by Doug A. Bowman, GPA: 4.00/4.00 Aug. 2021-Present

University of Cincinnati Cincinnati, OH, USA

B.S. in Computer Engineering with German Studies minor, GPA: 3.30/4.00 Aug. 2013-May 2018

Research Experience

Blacksburg, VA, USA Virginia Tech Jan. 2023-Present

Graduate Research Assistant

- Investigate the usage of extended reality technologies for time and place attributes of collaborative tasks

- Design and develop extended reality prototype applications according to project stakeholder specifications
- Report and publish findings from user studies evaluating prototype features

Lawrence Livermore National Laboratory

Computing Research Intern

Livermore, CA, USA May 2023-Aug. 2023

- Coordinated meetings with subject matter experts to derive a summer research initiative and objective
- Designed and developed virtual reality prototype applications to assist in remote collaborative processes
- Enhanced prototype capabilities following stakeholder evaluations and user study feedback

Blacksburg, VA, USA Virginia Tech

Graduate Research Assistant

May 2022-Aug. 2022

- Researched and identified knowledge gaps in avatar-mediated communication for extended reality
- Documented and presented systematically reviewed literature to stakeholders for proposed project approval
- Developed, evaluated, and published findings from the resulting extended reality prototype

Work Experience

JPMorgan Chase & Co.

Columbus, OH, USA

Associate Software Engineer I

Jul. 2018-Jul. 2021

- Lead development and design of Chase COVID Hub to assist and inform clients of available financial assistance
- Developed Chase Security Center to provide ease of access to client security and privacy settings
- Maintained and enhanced the Chase Offers feature across web and mobile platforms
- Acted as the subject matter expert for the behavioral-driven development initiative of Chase.com
- Documented and presented new feature highlights and advancements to project stakeholders

Siemens Healthineers

Software Engineer Intern

Forchheim, BY, DE Jan. 2017–Aug. 2017

- Developed a procedural management system to assist physician usage of advanced therapy devices
- Produced system architecture diagrams to document project design modifications and functionalities
- Participated in international software integration meetings utilizing both German and English languages

Granville Exempted Village Schools

Granville, OH, USA

Systems Administrator Intern

May 2016-Jul. 2016

- Managed Windows and Linux servers to maintain and improve school network infrastructure
- Regulated software updates to devices including operating systems and applications
- Lead a team of technicians to fulfill field service requests on behalf of school staff

Matrix Technologies, Inc.

Maumee, OH, USA

Computer Programmer and Systems Analyst Intern

Aug. 2015–Dec. 2015

- Conducted field service interviews with various stakeholders to distill features for user experience improvements
- Designed and developed internal software tools to automate project management processes
- Evaluated software tool quality in accordance with end-user feedback to improve existing tool capabilities

Matrix Technologies, Inc.

Maumee, OH, USA

Computer Programmer and Systems Analyst Intern

Aug. 2014-Dec. 2014

- Developed a managerial dashboard for tracking project data including financial and engineering documents
- Proposed, implemented, and evaluated front-end design changes for improved end-user application experience
- Participated in multi-disciplinary planning meetings to add and supplement the application feature backlog

Publications

Peer Reviewed Journal Papers

J1. A. Giovannelli, J. Thomas, L. Lane, F. Rodrigues and D. A. Bowman, "Gestures vs. Emojis: Comparing Non-Verbal Reaction Visualizations for Immersive Collaboration," in *IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics*, vol. 29, no. 11, pp. 4772-4781, Nov. 2023, doi: 10.1109/TVCG.2023.3320254.

Peer Reviewed Conference Papers

- C1. F. Rodrigues, A. Giovannelli, L. Pavanatto, H. Miao, J. C. d. Oliveira and D. A. Bowman, "AMP-IT and WISDOM: Improving 3D Manipulation for High-Precision Tasks in Virtual Reality," in 2023 IEEE International Symposium on Mixed and Augmented Reality (ISMAR), Sydney, Australia, 2023, pp. 303-311, doi: 10.1109/ISMAR59233.2023.00045.
- C2. **A. Giovannelli**, L. Lisle, and D. A. Bowman, "Exploring the impact of visual information on intermittent typing in virtual reality", in 2022 IEEE International Symposium on Mixed and Augmented Reality (ISMAR), 2022, pp. 8–17, doi: 10.1109/ISMAR55827.2022.00014.

Peer Reviewed Workshops, Posters, Abstracts, & Contests

- W1. L. Lane, A. Giovannelli, I. A. Tahmid, F. Rodrigues, C. Ilo, D. Hsu, C. Lougiakis, S. Davari, and D. A. Bowman, "The Alchemist: A Gesture-Based 3D User Interface for Engaging Arithmetic Calculations", to appear in 2024 IEEE Conference on Virtual Reality and 3D User Interfaces Abstracts and Workshops (VRW), 2024.
- W2. I. A. Tahmid, F. Rodrigues, A. Giovannelli, L. Lisle, J. Thomas and D. A. Bowman, "CoLT: Enhancing Collaborative Literature Review Tasks with Synchronous and Asynchronous Awareness Across the Reality-Virtuality Continuum," in 2023 IEEE International Symposium on Mixed and Augmented Reality Adjunct (ISMAR-Adjunct), Sydney, Australia, 2023, pp. 831-836, doi: 10.1109/ISMAR-Adjunct60411.2023.00183.

- W3. A. Giovannelli, F. Rodrigues, S. Davari, I. A. Tahmid, L. Lane, C. Connor, K. Davidson, G. N. Ramirez, B. David-John, and D. A. Bowman, "Clue hog: An immersive competitive lock-unlock experience using hook on go-go technique for authentication in the metaverse", in 2023 IEEE Conference on Virtual Reality and 3D User Interfaces Abstracts and Workshops (VRW), 2023, pp. 945-946, doi: 10.1109/VRW58643.2023.00315.
- W4. J. Thomas, S. W. Lee, **A. Giovannelli**, L. Lane, and D. Bowman, "A communication-focused framework for understanding immersive collaboration experiences", in 2023 IEEE Conference on Virtual Reality and 3D User Interfaces Abstracts and Workshops (VRW), 2023, pp. 301–304, doi: 10.1109/VRW58643.2023.00070.
- W5. L. Lisle, F. Lu, S. Davari, I. A. Tahmid, **A. Giovannelli**, C. Llo, L. Pavanatto, L. Zhang, L. Schlueter, and D. A. Bowman, "Clean the ocean: An immersive vr experience proposing new modifications to go-go and wim techniques", in 2022 IEEE Conference on Virtual Reality and 3D User Interfaces Abstracts and Workshops (VRW), 2022, pp. 920–921, doi: 10.1109/VRW55335.2022.00311.
- W6. E. Mohammadrezaei, A. Giovannelli, L. Lane, and D. Gračanin, "A digital twin based approach to smart lighting design", in 2022 Winter Simulation Conference (WSC), 2022.

PROJECTS

- Guided Tours for Multiscale Collaborative Virtual Environments

 Jul. 2023–Jul. 2024

 Design and prototype a virtual environment for collaborative multiscale inspection processes
- Surface Generation for Extended Reality Collaboration Jun. 2022–Sept. 2023

 Prototype and test a multi-user environment for creating and collaborating on shared surfaces

Awards

• Davenport Leadership Fellowship	2023 – 2024
• I/ITSEC Leonard P. Gollobin Scholarship	2023
• Best Conference Paper Honorable Mention IEEE ISMAR 2022 [C2]	2022
• Best 3DUI Contest Entry [W5]	2022
• International Co-op Program Scholarship	2016 – 2017
• Matrix Technologies, Inc. Co-op Scholarship	2014 – 2016

Professional Service

• Committee Member	2024–Present
Inaugural member of the Virtual Experience Research Accelerator (VERA) Ethics and Privacy Comm	ittee
• Member of Computer Science Graduate Student Council	2021-Present
Represent the interests of the CS graduate student body and assist in event planning	
• Member of the Center for Human-Computer Interaction	2021-Present
Actively participate in seminars at the Center focusing on the study of human-computer interaction	
• Communications Chair	2023
Developed and moderated discussion platforms for the 2024 IEEE VR conference	
• Student Volunteer	2023
Assisted in event operations at the 2023 IEEE International Symposium on Mixed and Augmented Re-	ality
• Student Volunteer	2023

Assisted in event operations at the 2023 IEEE VR satellite event

Student Volunteer

2022

Assisted in event operations at the 2022 IEEE International Symposium on Mixed and Augmented Reality

Teaching

• Graduate Teaching Assistant at Virginia Tech	Aug. 2022–Dec. 2022
Comparative Languages (CS-3304)	
• Graduate Teaching Assistant at Virginia Tech Software Design & Data Structures (CS-2114)	Jan. 2022–May 2022
• Graduate Teaching Assistant at Virginia Tech Software Design & Data Structures (CS-2114)	Aug. 2021–Dec. 2021

SKILLS

Programming Languages: C#, Python, JavaScript, Java, HTML, CSS

Productivity Tools: Unity, Git, JMP, SPSS, LaTeX, Tableau